Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to
be looking at how to make esters and
with this particular reaction making
esters is in the name right so it's
esterification where this reaction takes
a carboxylic acid and it reacts with an
alcohol to form an ester and water and
particularly this is in the presence of
an acid catalyst and with So, most of
the time this is done in the fume hood,
in the lab, maybe on a hot plate, where
it will take several minutes to really
show how this particular chemical can
come about because esters are part of
some of our sweetest smelling chemicals
that we commonly find from fruits or
from different perfumes or colognes.
So a lot of the smells
that we tend to enjoy.
So with this one, right, as I
mentioned before, it's all about
trying to see, okay, we have a
carboxylic acid and an alcohol, which
I have both of them written here.
Now, what exactly are
we going to be doing?
Well, as you can kind of see,
one of the products is water.
So what I did is, is I highlighted
the important part here.
And you can see in blue, right,
we have, oops, if we have
these two entire blue portions.
Well, what exactly can you see?
Well, we see H2O.
And what that's going to tell
us is that we're going to be
removing water in this reaction.
So esterification is a form
of condensation reaction.
So you think of condensation
that forms on the morning dew or
on the windshield of your car.
Think about water.
So with this one, what we are going
to actually do is we are going to
be removing H2O from our reaction,
so H2O will come off as a product.
So now when that happens, it's going to
be like the same idea as if you take a
straw and you were to like suck up a drink
from it, well, what's it going to do?
It's going to vacuum that
whole thing together.
So we're going to take our carboxylic
acid and our alcohol and we're
going to vacuum them together.
So that's essentially what is the idea.
So when we do that under
the right conditions.
We'll have our -COOH and we'll keep
R O, and what that's going to do,
it's going to be connecting to the
other R group on the other side.
Okay, so R will go on the right, and now
we have what we refer to as an ester.
So we had an ester, the carboxylic acid,
and the alcohol, plus water, right?
Water is a product as well.
So this is a very common reaction
that we don't, we don't only see in
organic chemistry, but in introductory
biochemistry too, because this is how
carbohydrates connect to each other,
how lipids can connect to each other,
how amino acids can make proteins.
So, trying, so not only
esterification, but just condensation
in general, so removing the water.
Now, let's take a look at some
different examples and how, how you
might see this in the classroom.
All right.
So our first example of doing an
esterification, so most, most likely
what you're going to get is a carboxylic
acid in an alcohol component, component.
So if we look really closely, we can
see the carboxylic acid on the left.
And then we have our alcohol on the right.
Now the whole idea about this is
setting it up so that way you can
easily see how the -OH components are
going to be pointing at each other.
So my first tip is to point
the OH's towards each other.
O H's.
Toward one another now.
So when you do that, it will
actually align up how we're going
to be removing the water component.
So what we're gonna do is we're
gonna rewrite our structure.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4 with an oh and with
a double bond, and we are going to flip
the alcohol so that way you have the h
o and then the CH3 on the other side.
Now, what we can see is, if you notice,
you can see H2O on our structure.
So we're going to be removing water
from this particular structure.
So water's going to go away, and
as a result, we're going to be
bringing them together again.
So as the reaction takes place,
what will happen is we're
going to be making an ester.
So, remember, the carbon
chain stays the same.
The only thing that we are changing
is the functional group about this.
So we're going from a carboxylic
acid and an alcohol to an ester.
Alright, so we'll redraw our carbon chain.
Put our double bonded oxygen with an O.
Connected to this CH3 from
the right hand structure.
So if you can kind of notice here, just
to kind of color code it, right, is
now we have an ester on our structure.
So it changed exactly how
it would function, right?
It changed how it functions,
how it smells, how it interacts.
Um, and how it's going to behave, right?
Um, especially when you think
of carboxylic acids, right?
They're very acidic.
They will, they also can do hydrogen
bonding, same thing with alcohols, and
then it trades it away to do something
that's a little bit more stable.
It tends to be something that, uh,
can only do dipole dipole forces,
a very, very different structure.
Let's go through a bunch of
example problems and make
sure you solidified this down.
And as, as you're going through
them, I would fully recommend trying
to pause the video and see if that,
uh, if you're able to do them when
I present these next problems.
Okay, so in our very first question, which
is all about predicting the product of the
following reactions, and as I mentioned
before, if you're interested in trying to
pause it to solve it yourself, please do.
There'll be three examples to go through.
So with this one, it's butanol
and methanoic acid are going
to be reacting together.
So as before, we're going to be taking
it where we remove the water component.
So we have H2O is what is
going to be removed, right?
So the water is going to come off and be
one of our products of our final reaction.
Now when these two are
coming together, right?
So we'll keep our carbon chain.
So we still have the four carbons.
from the alcohol, and what is going to
be remaining is the O from that alcohol
connecting to the C double bond O.
And then our hydrogen that is
coming off from the other structure.
So I just highlighted the ester
so that way you can see it and
experience all those different colors.
So with this one, it's
actually a very unique ester.
So this one smells like plums.
So like I mentioned, a lot of them
have these really cool smells and
aromas to them, um, for when you
go through actually trying to name
them and understand them, uh, and,
and go through that entire process.
So, let's try to do another problem
that's very, very similar to this.
So, we're going to go through
that condensation reaction.
Now, as you can notice too, you
can see that the O is written
on the left side or the right.
Um, just kind of that little example.
It doesn't matter which side it's written
on, but it does matter when it comes
to naming it and trying to identify it.
So that way you do realize that,
um, as you are going through these
different types of reactions.
So, with this one here, right, this
one looks very, very different.
So we have salicylic acid and acetic
acid, and these are going to be reacting.
Now, with this one, it's very, uh, you
gotta be very careful to make sure you are
identifying what each of the groups are so
that way it bonds to the correct location.
Um, big thing is on this structure, right?
We have an acetic acid.
So it's a carboxylic acid that is going to
react with an alcohol, which is over here.
So this one's going to bond
to the bottom right one.
Now, through this esterification, it's
one of the most common esterifications
most organic chemistry students learn,
um, especially because it leads to the
production of aspirin, um, which most
students tend to do that synthesis
when they are in organic chemistry.
We are going to be removing the water
component, so when these two things
come together, we're going to be...
Uh, we are going to be taking out
the H2O, so just these pieces here.
Right now when H2O comes off, we are
going to be making a new structure.
So we will redraw our ring, uh, like
how it goes from a hexagon to a circle
We will draw our benzene
ring, have our -COOH  on top.
And then on the bottom, we're going to
have another very similar looking thing,
but instead it's going to be an ester.
So we have our O connected to our
double bond, and then we had one
carbon that is off just like so.
So this is going to be aspirin.
Or salicylic or, or very uh, or
methyl salicylic acid for this one.
All right, so this is our aspirin
we're, that we are going to be making.
Let's do another.
So with this one, we have acetic acid and
pentol, which is a really common reaction
that you can also do in labs, especially
because this one can smell like bananas.
So when, when, after, if you make
the product correctly, that is
welcome to organic chemistry, where
not everything works all the time.
So we're going to be removing the H2O.
So H2O is what's going to be coming off.
Now when that happens, we
will remove that component.
And then we will bring together
the other pieces, right?
So we have our carboxylic
acid turned to ester.
Then we will attach it
to the five member chain.
And you know what?
Being that this is kind of shoved
in the corner, let's redraw it,
or let's just blow it up, and we
will put it on the other side.
We will have one, two, three, four,
Uh, five carbons for our specific
chain here, um, for our compound.
And then we can see that we have
made a pentyl ethanoate as our
final answer or trying to name it.
So we made our ester.
Hopefully this video showing how esters
are made is something that did help you.
So going through multiple
different examples, right?
So going through four different examples.
Uh, if you want to learn about how it
breaks apart, please consider watching
my follow up video to this, which goes
through the process of hydrolysis.
Thank you so much for watching.
Please hit that like and subscribe
video and please keep helping the
channel grow and let comment below
and let me know what you thought.
And if there's any particular videos
that you would like to see in the future.
All right now, bye now.